# ESTEBAN A. SANTOS

Dallas, Tx 75150

Phone: 787-605-4541 | Email: <u>santosesteban09@gmail.com</u> LinkedIn: https://www.linkedin.com/in/esteban-santos-55b717b0/ |

GitHub: https://github.com/PRicoSaint |

Portfolio:https://shrouded-waters-22536.herokuapp.com/

#### SUMMARY

Full Stack Web Developer with 8 years of background in Manufacturing. Effective at combining creativity and problem solving to develop user-friendly applications. Known among colleagues for strong wit and attention to detail no matter the complexity of the project, and recently earned a Certificate in Full Stack Web Development from Southern Methodist University in Dallas, Tx.

#### TECHNICAL SKILLS

**Languages:** CSS, HTML, JavaScript **Databases:** MySQL, MongoDB

**Tools:** Git and Heroku

**Productivity:** Word, Powerpoint, Excel

CMMS: EAM, MP2, SAP

**Additional Skills:** Basic Electrical wiring and equipment troubleshooting

#### **PROJECTS**

# Gear-Out! | github.com/PRicoSaint/Gear\_Out | quiet-garden-76902.herokuapp.com/

- Full stack app modeling fully functioning e-commerce site where users can rent and/or buy costumes.
- Originated main idea and provided project direction
- Integrated Stripe and implemented functioning cart
- Javascript, MongoDB, Apollo (server and client), Graphql

# S.W.O.R.D | github.com/PRicoSaint/S.W.O.R.D | frozen-harbor-76666.herokuapp.com/

- Full stack app incorporating a work order tracking system, User sign-up and login as well as table exporting.
- Provided project direction (Super hero)
- Implemented main work order table display and integrated export functionality
- Javascript, CSS, handlebars, MySQL

#### Food for your Brews |

# github.com/PRicoSaint/FoodforyourBrews | pricosaint.github.io/FoodforyourBrews/

- Simple app that pulls data from two separate API's and marries together to help the user find the perfect match of food/meal and their beer of their choice.
- Originated main idea and gave project direction
- Developed and styled homepage, integrating API into app
- Javascript, HTML, CSS, Materialize, External API's

# Workout Tracker | github.com/PRicoSaint/P.R.SaintExerciseTrackerDeluxe | stormy-citadel-59650.herokuapp.com/

- Full stack app that accepts exercise input and tracks workouts. It displays the past 7 days of data in user-friendly graphs.
- Implemented back-end functionality, integrating MongoDB and REST API queries
- Javascript, CSS, MongoDB

### **E**XPERIENCE

## **Maintenance Supervisor** 2019 – 2021

**Pepsico** Dallas, TX Headed maintenance staff in Union environment; completing repairs and preventative maintenance activities that include all Gatorade Lines as well as Utilities. *Key Accomplishments:* 

• Chaired L2 28oz rebuild for 2020 ensuring continued continued line performance **Maintenance Supervisor** 2018 – 2019

**Owens Corning** Dallas, TX Planned and executed Daily and weekly Work orders using SAP based system. *Key Accomplishments:* 

• Coordinated Team of 6 mechanics to troubleshoot and fix mechanical issues, improving equipment uptime

# **Maintenance and Reliability Engineer** 2015 – 2018

**Hormel Foods** Various Directed team of Maintenance craftsmen in the execution of Preventative Maintenance strategies, equipment reliability improvement, and meeting Production needs. Oversaw maintenance planning and execution for plant utilities and Animal Feed operation. *Key Accomplishments:* 

- Built and drove Preventative maintenance program and work request system from ground up
- Key member in multimillion dollar Spice system upgrade project. Designed and implemented a complete system of PM's and spare parts for over 100 assets with input from production, engineering and the OEM.

#### **Manufacturing Engineer** 2013–2015

**General Mills** Cedar Rapids, IA Led and owned all technical aspects of the Fruit by the Foot System. Responsibilities included production reliability, scrap reduction, and production throughput improvements. *Key Accomplishments:* 

- Lead the selection, testing and implementation of Equipment upgrades in order to improve production line reliability, increase operator safety, and deliver cost savings of \$20,000 (Videojet Inkjet printers)
- Identified and increased the uptime (MTBF) of the process bottleneck by 38%. These improvements produced 2% increased output and reduced scrap by \$200,000

#### **EDUCATION**

**Bootcamp Certificate:** Southern Methodist University, Dallas, TX

A 24-week intensive program focused on gaining technical programming skills in HTML5, CSS3, Javascript, JQuery, Bootstrap, Node.js, MySQL, MongoDB, Express, Handelbars.js, React, Apollo, GraphQL.

**Bachelors in Electrical Engineering:** University of Puerto Rico, Mayaguez, PR August 2007 - December 2012

5 year course in electrical engineering with a focus on power systems.